video here is understanding the history
and purpose of markdown why would you
even need markdown and somebody as
somebody Ronnie very wisely said why not
just stick to the thing that's the most
common and the most popular that's
exactly what we're going to do um and
it's very imper it's very important that
you understand that about this approach
to learning markdown because markdown is
one of these technologies that started
out as a good idea and then went and it
like expanded like crazy and there's so
many fractions factions sorry uh and
split it and forks and everything of the
language then for a beginner they can
get very confused not to mention the
fact that markdown isn't even taught
anywhere raise your hand if you've been
taught
markdown raise your hand if you've been
taught officially you've been taught
markdown in any course
whatsoever they do not cover it they do
not cover markdown it's one of these
things that you're expected to just pick
up and yet it's the critical way of
writing in pretty much every single
technical role whatsoever and let's talk
about that for a second let's talk about
how markdown has permeated the whole
world okay so markdown at this current
time we'll talk about the history but at
this current time markdown is used
everywhere if you're writing slack
messages you you slack right you when
you want to put italics around something
you're using markdown um unfortunately
WebEx and some of the other techn
decided not to use markdown and to
invent their own you know syntax or way
of you know doing highlighting and stuff
so let's do a little bit about the
history of markdown in fact let's let's
go ahead and ask Chad GPT what Chad GPT
says and um so this is Chad
GPT uh let's do a clear
here uh what is the history of markdown
actually let's use capital M which is
the official oh gosh
uh Mark Mark one
markdown you took cs23
markdown CS
203 and why are we not learning
restructure tests right all right this
is these are all good
questions um okay so let's see what chat
GPT says let's see if it's right um Mark
out is a lightweight markup languages
perform editing plain texts okay by the
way what is a markup language a markup
language is a language that uses other
symbols or words um to change the
presentation of the language and
somebody of you are really really old if
you want to date yourself here if you go
back
to uh ancient times uh I'm going to say
it textmate so when computers first came
out we all we had was the terminal right
and if you wanted to emphasize something
you put stars around it right the little
Aster Stars around it uh if you wanted
to underline something you put a little
you know underline symbols around it uh
not stml hell no this is way before that
was even invented um but you know word
processors back in the day were perfect
it included I'm really dating myself
here but at the time if you wanted that
kind of thing before I even made it to
your printer um you would you know to to
have metallics you would do a thing to
it it was it wasn't at the time you
couldn't even use a mouse I know that's
how I'm really dating myself right but
markdown in many ways is that it you go
all the way back to marking up text so
you mix text with something else back
let me just show you as you can see
where this is actually the text of the
skill stack website right now and this
is an example of what we mean by this so
by putting we're going to go through all
the syntax here but by putting a hashtag
here or formally an octo Thorp we can
say that this thing here is a title and
so when we go to the website we can go
see uh the title so here it is and
rendered this is the same document I'm
working on right now you can see it's
been rendered as a title and he even put
an Octor there um and you can see the
first thing here you can see these
bullet points and then look it's
actually automatically numbering them so
this is an example of markdown and it's
also an example of a markup language a
markup language is a language that is
textual that allows s the use of other
symbols to create special meaning what
are what's up with all the ones over
here we're going to talk about that
right that symbolizes the beginning of
an ordered list and and not numbered
list an ordered list so these brackets
around this indicate that this is a a
link and this here is the URL that would
that'll be you know your web browser
would use when you click on it okay so
this here this this that's what we mean
by markup languages so let's continue to
read so
uh mark down which is obviously a play
on the term mark up uh was created by
John grber and Aaron Schwarz in 2004
with the goal of allowing people oh
thank you for that uh uh allowing people
to write using an easy to read and easy
to write plain text format optionally
convert optionally convert it to
structured valid XML H HTML which we're
going to learn you're like why aren't we
learning HTML first because markdown is
easier and we'll talk about this John
grber a writer and Tech blogger this is
so important my friends markdown was
invented by a
writer HTML was invented by a
scientist
okay and it's it's becomes really
obvious right because so markdown was
invented by John Gruber who wanted
basically a language to be as readable
as possible arguing that users should be
able to understand a language with
without the help of tags and other
formatting features found in more
complex languages like HTML which
somebody mentioned
HTML was the original scientific very
crazy language that only you know
scientists with a certain degree could
understand and to this day HTML was
still pretty hard to understand let me
show you just to inspect element on your
web page this is HTML my
friends do you think the average person
can come in here and read this and
understand it nope they cannot so what
can they understand this this is what
they can understand and they can write
even with a text based editor okay so
that was the purpose behind John grber
and here's good old Aaron Schwarz the B
boost is dedicated in part to Aaron
Schwarz who at 15 has done many amazing
things there's a whole video about him
John Gruber coordinated with Aaron
Schwarz a Renown computer programmer for
co-founding social media and Reddit
thank you for that follow um and
contributing to the development of RSS
his activism is everything Aeron was
also involved with the grber with John
grber in the creating of these people
the bottom line these writers wanted a
way to write quickly and that could
easily be translated into a web page and
they did not want to write HTML and this
year this is the first year we're going
to learn markdown first before we learn
HTML and then we're going to learn HTML
from the conversion of markdown into
HTML which you'll then be be able to see
in fact markdown is a really great way
to get the idea of mixing markup you
know using markup in a in a
humanfriendly way before you jump into
the more much more complicated world of
HTML not many people do it this way I'm
glad we're doing it this way so markdown
has been adopted by many platforms as a
text to HTML conversion tool it's used
by writers and developers of websites
like GitHub stack Overflow Reddit slack
in fact uh oh damn Party of Three
welcome okay so in fact the markdown
variant I'm making a video right now so
I'm just going to keep going in fact the
markdown variant used by GitHub known as
GitHub flavored markdown introduced
Syntax for task lists tables as well as
many other features useful in software
documentation I regularly use these tax
lists in my pull requests for GitHub and
um as you can see they're known for
GitHub is GitHub flavor markdown um we
mentioned in the overview video that we
will be getting into specifically GitHub
flavored markdown because it is the most
useful it is the most widely adopted
even though it is an extension to the
common Mark standard which we will get
to we're going to talk about all of that
very soon right now we're just talking
about the history so the Simplicity of
markdown uh has contributed to its
increasing popularity as many web
writers and developers integrate into
their workflow how however as usage is
grown so too have a number of markdown
flavors often leading to issues with
consistency and Capac ability despite
this markdown remains widely used and a
well- loved tool um and I can attest to
this I have you know deployed lots and
lots of documentation in my in my day
and including our current Enterprise uh
I deployed both of our Enterprise
internal and external facing um user
documentation for the company for the
job the the and I got you know I got
accolades from from people at at senior
levels of management for for promoting
the use of of a very easy to to use uh
documentation platform at work um
documentation is at the core of of any
technical job and knowing markdown is a
critical skill uh I would say for being
able to do anything else uh from the
beginning from just even
communicating um with emphasis um using
tools like slack and and other other
tools and um uh what's what's the other
one besides slack I can't
remember um what's the one besides slack
Discord Discord do too Discord and slack
both do the same thing um yeah and we'll
talk about there there have been other
um definitely other markup markdown Mar
yeah funny okay so so that's the history
the history is Mr Gruber wanted to make
something that he could write really
easily and a lot of times he was
converting an email into a website and
you we'll notice that when we get into
markdown you'll see remnants of email
old school 1980s email inside of
markdown so that's that's what we'll do
next